introducing the glute medius hip thrust
[Music]
so 10 years ago I wanted to show you
guys some footage from 2013. I came up
with this exercise I called double
standing hip abduction and basically
what I did was I was a little bit flexed
but I would start here and then go up
like this
so I would kind of go like
here
there and it's like
why did I not think of holding on to
something and why did I not think of
putting load here
the other thing I realized is you know
in physical therapy they have the hip
hike
you just laterally tilt so if you're
looking at like someone's shirt you'll
see it sink down this way your laterally
tilting you're stretching the glute
medius and then you just come up like
this
drop see how this leg this foot is
longer than this one
and then you straighten it out
so this is a hip hike if you do enough
reps of this you feel it really working
there
especially
what I've realized through this exercise
through coaching it so much now if you
kind of think laterally see how my leg
starts out hear it straight
it moves laterally and then I straighten
out and it moves this way that's a huge
glut meatus contraction right here
I feel this big time so I did what I did
was I took that idea from 20 2013
the double standing hip abduction and I
said let's do a few things to it let's
get in more of a stretch
into lateral pelvic tilt
let's hold on for stability and let's
put weight there
and so then I started calling it The
weighted hip hike because that's a hip
hike but at first I started having
people wear ankle weights and standing
on something they'd have ankle weights
on and just do this and then I realized
it works better because what people
don't realize it's this is if you move
this leg outwards yes you feel this a
little bit but it's this glute working
so what I do is I I started using ankle
weights and I would kind of go like this
and you really feel it okay but then I'm
like okay my ankle weights I've got two
10 Pounders so I can only do 20 pounds I
want more weight well then I thought I
really don't have to stand on anything
I could just do the same thing bend my
knee
and when I bend my knee it creates this
nice little shelf for the plate
now these BC strength plates are perfect
you want the ones with the handles
so grab on for stability
one thing you don't want to be too close
to here
you want to be far enough away that you
were your
kind of at an angle right off the bat
you want to start here this is loading
up the glute Medias in stretch I'm not
flexed at the hip
so from the side view I
I am right here I'm moving side to side
laterally
I'm not bending
and I'm not rotating
I'm not rotating like this
and I'm not flexed at the hip and I'm
not squatting people initially want to
squat that's all they know they've been
squatting for so long
so what I do is from here you can bend
the knee a little bit but not too much
so from here and you can start this out
with body weight don't try to use too
much weight right away do do body weight
a couple sessions before you start
adding load and you can just put your
hand on your hip
sink this way lateral tilt and move the
hip laterally
so see my shirt
this is level I'm sunken down see that
I'm shifting this leg laterally and this
shirt now is diagonal this is loading up
the glute medius and stretch and then I
use this glute to push laterally
push to the side and I raise this as
high as I can now one critical element
the two critical ailments to this are
well there are several one is you don't
want to bend over you want to stay in
the lateral plane the frontal plane the
second is to pre-stretch right there
like that to get the lateral tilt and
the lateral leg movement and the third
is to abduct all the way moving in the
frontal plane and then you see this pop
right there that see this
pop see that leg it moves boom right
there now I've got maximal shortening
here
so you have maximal lengthening maximum
shortening and one thing if you study
the leg
how much can it
can it adduct anyway you only have about
30 degrees so
if you you can either move you can
either add duct to 30 degrees or you can
lateral tilt 30 degrees but eventually
you run out of range of motion well you
got to practice this kind of sinking
into that hip
and you'll feel it stretch the glute
medius
so then once you do
tilt
pop
then you get in a rhythm
okay I'm already burning like crazy here
the next step is to use a plate
preferably a plate with handles
obviously use 10 pounds first
then 25 pounds when you're really
Advanced you can use the 45 and the
weight goes right here like this see how
it's a nice stable position sink
drive up pop
sink drive up
so
what I realized was
I'm doing 25 reps now
with the 45 pound plate
I don't like doing 25 reps of anything
I want to do 15 reps
obviously this is not an exercise where
you're going to do one at Max there's
not it's more like a 10 to 30 rep
movement
but I realize I can use a dumbbell you
just put it right here
so now I'm using a 60 pound dumbbell I
got 15 reps yesterday
you just have to make sure the dumbbell
goes right here
so it looks like this
okay and then when you do the other side
switch
here's what it looks like from behind
okay
shift stretch
so you see that
watch the leg
tilt push
and you feel that pop right here
don't go to here finish off right
there
we just got a study public showing hip
dose and squats they build the gluteus
maximus they don't build the glute
medius to maximize gluteus medius
hypertrophy you have to be doing frontal
plane movements you'll not you will not
maximize your shelf
by doing hip extension I love cable
abductions I love band abductions
we do a lot of different abduction but
this is my favorite and you know why
because all you need is something to
hold on to and a plate you can do that
anywhere this is the first highly
effective glute medius exercise that can
be done with free weights so in my
opinion everyone from around the world
should be doing this exercise whether
you're just
you know elderly training for functional
strength
glute medius helps prevent Falls or
you're an athlete looking to improve
your lateral agility or you're a bikini
competitor trying to build a shelf and
get more upward glute growth because in
bikini right now it's all about upper
glutes you need more upper glutes that's
what every judge is saying to the girls
you need more upper glutes you need more
upper glutes so this should be a staple
in your program I'm calling it The glute
media is hip to us because this is the
hip thrust for the glute medius yes
you're not thrusting your hips but it's
that good of an exercise and I think
that that name will stick it sounds
better than double standing hip
abduction it sounds better than the
weighted hip hike just remember to get
good at body weight first then add load
Progressive overload is only Progressive
overload when you use the same range of
motion and the same technique
so if you're doing body weight you know
nice and smooth like this
and then you
hold on to weight and you stop when you
see the common errors you stop getting
the stretch people just go from here and
then they won't come out that high and
they'll kind of heave and they'll be
like
like that and they're heaving it should
look nice and smooth
like this
[Music]
that's the glute media's hip thrust give
it a try ask me questions I will try my
best to answer them in the comments
section sorry for the long absence on
YouTube I'd like to offer an excuse but
I've just been overwhelmed that's it
thank you
[Music]